<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xmlstylesheet.xsl"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Last chapter of the first (american) edition of "The Magus"</title>
            <author>John Fowles (1926–2005)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Dovilė Gervytė</name>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <date>1965</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="chapter">
            <pb n="xxx"/>
            <head rend="align(center) underlined">Seventy-eight</head>
            <p>[...]</p>
            <div2 type="section">
               <pb n="605"/>
               <ab n="1" type="narrative_unit" xml:id="F3"><!-- CSS: green -->
                  <s n="1">Her eyes were wet, perhaps with the pain. But she was slowly smiling.
                     That archaic smile, her variant of theirs, steadier, braver, far less
                     implacable, without malice or arrogance, yet still that smile.</s>
                  <s n="2" rend="first-line-indent"><seg xml:id="AP_F3">Mocking love, yet making
                        it.</seg></s>
               </ab>
               <ab n="2" type="narrative_unit" xml:id="F4"><!-- CSS: blue -->
                  <s n="3" rend="first-line-indent">And suddenly the truth came to me, as we stood
                     there, trembling, searching, at our point of fulcrum. There were no watching
                     eyes. The windows were as blank as they looked. The theatre was empty. It was
                     not a theatre. They had told her it was a theatre, and she had believed them,
                     and I had believed her. To bring us to this–not for themselves, but for us. I
                     turned and looked at the windows, the facade, the pompous white pedimental
                     figures.</s>
                  <s n="4" rend="first-line-indent">Then she buried her face in her hands, as if
                     some inexorable mechanism had started.</s>
                  <s n="5" rend="first-line-indent">I was so sure. It was logical, the
                     characteristic and perfect final touch to the godgame. They had absconded. <seg
                        xml:id="AP_F4">I was so sure, and yet . . . after so much, how could I be
                        perfectly sure?</seg> How could they be so cold? So inhuman? So incurious?
                     So load the dice and yet leave the game? And if I wasn’t sure?</s>
               </ab>
               <pb n="606"/>
               <ab n="3" type="narrative_unit" xml:id="F1"><!-- CSS: orange -->
                  <s n="6" rend="first-line-indent">I gave her bowed head one last stare, then <seg
                        xml:id="AP_F1">I was walking</seg>. Firmer than Orpheus, as firm as Alison
                     herself, that other day of parting, not once looking back. </s>
               </ab>
               <ab n="4" type="narrative_unit" xml:id="F5"><!-- CSS: grey -->
                  <s n="7">The autumn grass, the autumn sky. People. A blackbird, poor fool, singing
                     out of season from the willows by the lake. A flight of gray pigeons over the
                     houses. Fragments of freedom, an anagram made flesh. And somewhere <seg
                        xml:id="AP_F5">the stinging smell of burning leaves</seg>.</s>
               </ab>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
