<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="xmlstylesheet.xsl"?>
<TEI version="3.3.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Last chapter of the revised (american) edition of "The Magus"</title>
            <author>John Fowles (1926–2005)</author>
            <respStmt>
               <name>Dovilė Gervytė</name>
               <resp>editor</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <imprint>
                     <date>1977</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="en">English</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div1 type="chapter">
            <pb n="xxx"/>
            <head rend="align(center) underlined">Chapter Seventy-eight</head>
            <p>[...]</p>
            <div2 type="section">
               <pb n="654"/>
               <ab n="1" type="narrative_unit" xml:id="F3"><!-- CSS: green -->
                  <s n="1">Her hand stayed over the side of her face and her eyes were growing wet,
                     certainly with the pain and perhaps partly also with <seg xml:id="AP_F3">a sort
                        of incredulity</seg>.</s>
               </ab>
               <ab n="2" type="narrative_unit" xml:id="F4"><!-- CSS: blue -->
                  <s n="2" rend="first-line-indent">The final truth came to me, as we stood there,
                     trembling, searching, between all our past and all our future; at a moment when
                     the difference between fission and fusion by in a nothing, a tiniest movement,
                     betrayal, further misunderstanding.</s>
                  <s n="3" rend="first-line-indent">The final truth came to me, as we stood there,
                     trembling, searching, between all our past and all our future; at a moment when
                     the difference between fission and fusion by in a nothing, a tiniest movement,
                     betrayal, further misunderstanding.</s>
                  <s n="4" rend="first-line-indent">There were no watching eyes. The windows were as
                     blank as they looked. The theatre was empty. It was not a theatre. They had
                     perhaps told her it was a theatre, and she had believed them, and I <pb n="655"
                     /> had believed her. Perhaps it had all been to bring me to this, to give me my
                     last lesson and final ordeal... the task, as in <emph rend="italic"
                        >L'Astrée</emph>, of turning lions and unicorns and magi and other mythical
                     monsters into stone statues. I looked away from Alison and at those distant
                     windows, the façade, the pompous white pedimental figures that crowned it. It
                     was logical, the perfect climax to the godgame. They had absconded, we were
                        alone.<seg xml:id="AP_F4">I was so sure, and yet... after so much, how could
                        I be perfectly sure?</seg> How could they be so cold, so inhuman – so
                     incurious? So load the dice and yet leave the game?</s>
               </ab>
               <ab n="3" type="narrative_unit" xml:id="xx"><!-- CSS: [-] -->
                  <s n="5" rend="first-line-indent">I looked back towards the path. The far more
                     natural watchers there were strolling on, as if this trivial little bit of
                     masculine brutality, the promised scene, had lost their interest also. Alison
                     hadn't moved, she still held a hand to her cheek, but now her head was bowed.
                     There was a little shuddered outbreath as she tried to stifle the tears; then
                     her voice, broken, hardly audible, in despair, almost self-amazed.</s>
               </ab>
               <ab n="4" type="narrative_unit" xml:id="F1"><!-- CSS: orange -->
                  <s n="6" rend="first-line-indent">'I hate you. I <emph rend="italic">hate</emph>
                     you.'</s>
                  <s n="7" rend="first-line-indent">I said nothing, made no move to touch her. After
                     a moment she looked up and everything in her expression was as it had been in
                     her voice and words: hatred, pain, every female resentment since time began.
                     But I clung to something, the something I had never seen, or always feared to
                     see, in those intense grey eyes, the quintessential something behind all the
                     hating, the hurtness, the tears. A small step poised, a shattered crystal
                     waiting to be reborn. She spoke again, as if to kill what I was looking at.</s>
                  <s n="8" rend="first-line-indent">'I <emph rend="italic">do</emph>.'</s>
                  <s n="9" rend="first-line-indent">'Then <seg xml:id="AP_F1">why wouldn't you let
                        me walk away?</seg>'</s>
                  <s n="10" rend="first-line-indent">She shook her abruptly lowered head, as if the
                     question was unfair.</s>
                  <s n="11" rend="first-line-indent">'You know why.'</s>
                  <s n="12" rend="first-line-indent">'No.'</s>
                  <s n="13" rend="first-line-indent">'I knew within two seconds of seeing you.'</s>
                  I went closer. Her other hand went to her face, as if I might hit her again. 'I
                  understand that word now, Alison. Your word.' Still she waited, face hidden in her
                  hands, like someone being told of a tragic loss. 'You can't hate someone who's
                  really on his knees. Who'll never be more than half a human being without you.' <s
                     n="14" rend="first-line-indent">The bowed head, the buried face.</s>
                  <pb n="656"/>
               </ab>
               <ab n="5" type="narrative_unit" xml:id="F5"><!-- CSS: grey -->
                  <s n="15" rend="first-line-indent">She is silent, she will never speak, never
                     forgive, never reach a hand, never leave this frozen present tense. All waits,
                     suspended. Suspend the autumn trees, the autumn sky, anonymous people. A
                     blackbird, poor fool, sings out of season from the willows by the lake. A
                     flight of pigeons over the houses; fragments of freedom, hazard, an anagram
                     made flesh. And somewhere <seg xml:id="AP_F5">the stinging smell of burning
                        leaves</seg>.</s>
               </ab>
            </div2>
         </div1>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>

